In Trimdon, their man was front-runner to become the youngest Labour leader ever In Trimdon, their man was front-runner to become the youngest Labour leader ever If he hadn't come and knocked on the door that night, Tony Blair would not have become the Prime Minister.
Tony had the great knack of kind of shrugging off the political burdens and so forth and he could talk to you as a real friend, just where you'd left off.
Yes, I went on Against The War and I don't think it will necessarily have made him feel badly about me.
I went on getting Christmas cards from him.
Tony Blair didn't shake my hand, Tony Blair didn't offer me his hand and I would have to think seriously whether I would shake that hand.
He said, "I just want to thank you for everything you've done.
"I'll only say this once and that's it."
And it was just a very special moment.
I'd been getting fairly desperate to fight the election.
I could see everything disappearing and then Sedgefield came up about three weeks before the General Election in 1983.
I remember sitting there thinking, "Is it really worth trying to have a go yet again?"
Then I decided, "Yes, I'll do it."
So he phoned me up and asked if he could come.
I said, "Yes, we have a meeting tomorrow."
We also wanted a few beers and to actually watch a football match that was on that night.
He sat down and unfortunately it was a draw at full time.
It was a draw at extra time and it went on to penalties.
He sat there for about two-and-a-half hours, I think.
So who was the man asking to become Labour candidate in the newly-created constituency of Sedgefield?
Tony Blair wasn't a total stranger to County Durham.
He went to school in the city and his dad lectured at the university.
The Northeast hadn't been home for many years by the time the young Blair set out to find a job in politics.
He'd had one go already and lost a by-election, but won one big fan.
Whatever the result, we believe he has a big future in British politics.
The Labour Party was down on its knees at that time.
He was like a breath of fresh air, really.
I can remember saying to him, "You're a bit posh to be the MP for round here."
There was something special.
We never said he was going to be Prime Minister, obviously.
But I think you knew he was certainly Cabinet material and very special.
And so, by winning over these five men in John Burton's front room, Tony Blair set himself on the path to Downing Street.
Within days, he found himself selected to fight Sedgefield, the last available seat in the country, and he did so with a touch of showbiz.
He was interested in walking around the constituency with Cherie's stepmother, Pat Phoenix - Elsie Tanner from Coronation Street.
Everybody was following this with great fascination.
He was a bit like pied piper, taking his little troop round the constituency with him.
The hard, raw policies didn't really seem to interest him.
Our dining room became a campaign headquarters, just about.
There was a map on the wall and it got taken over.
It was quite exciting.
He was the great charmer and everyone liked him.
He was on stage and he's a very formidable operator when he's on stage.
Predictably, in a Labour heartland, the Labour man won and the new MP started to cultivate a circle of friends he could trust.
After the Mass, I brought them up here for a cup of coffee.
He spotted a tennis racket and he said, "I'm going to be up every weekend in the constituency.
"I love tennis.
Would you be able to slot me "into whatever group you play with?"
I promised him I would and that began a regular tennis partnership and games for about the next ten years.
Once Tony got elected, he was looking for a house right away in the constituency.
I said, "I've got a house for you."
He said, "What do you mean?"
I says, "One Chris and I have been looking at.
"Here's a survey, here's what you need to be bidding if you want to get it."
And he went off and he fell in love with it, thought it was brilliant.
We're Tony Blair's next-door neighbours and we live 50 yards away from his house, Mirabella.
Every weekend he'd be playing football with the boys.
Yeah.
We used to chat over the fence when he was playing football on the lawn or whatever he was doing.
As parents, you can't fault them.
They don't mind getting dirty, they don't mind getting down to it.
The children are the most important thing to them.
It's pretty hectic practically every weekend.
You've got your surgeries, there's all sorts of things.
To me, the constituency is the base from which everything else comes and upon which everything else is built.
"The children are in their pyjamas, all ready for bed."
But Mirabella wasn't a full-time family home for long.
The constituency home hasn't really been a family home, I don't think, since probably '85, '86, because he has relocated to Islington, although it has been very good for him, in an image way, to come from this peculiar place called the North.
And it was from the battered, industrial heart of the Northeast that Tony Blair witnessed a decade of sea-change in politics.
Sedgefield, he said, told him something.
'One of the mistakes people often make about areas 'like County Durham is that they think everyone' has this romantic nostalgia about the past.
What they actually are addressing most of their lives is a better future for themselves.
He moved from being a backbench, bog-standard MP into becoming a major figure in the Labour Party within two years, really.
The relationship really changed from an MP on the phone, desperately trying to show somebody, anybody that he was doing things, into a politician who was of some stature nationally.
I regret to have to report to the House the death of the Right Honourable John Smith, QC.
And so with the loss of his leader and friend, Sedgefield's MP faced a momentous decision.
I had this real sense of personal grief at the same time as not being able to escape the fact that there was an issue that was direct and immediate, namely did I go for becoming leader of the Labour Party or not.
In Trimdon, their man was front-runner to become the youngest Labour leader ever and they were well and truly in the spotlight.
I therefore declare that Tony Blair is elected Leader of the Labour Party.
A day later, and the new Leader of the Opposition is welcomed home.
A big day for two six-year-olds.
I'm not sure who started it but someone was ringing everyone who was going and trying to find Gary Glitter, Leader Of The Pack to play when he got off the train but in hindsight it's probably a good thing that we didn't find it.
Everyone was cheering, clapping.
That was our cue to be very nervous.
Start smiling, like.
I remember us both being given a rose and I remember asking why we had them.
Someone said, "You'll find out in a minute."
I didn't actually know what was happening until we got pushed in front of a camera.
I'm not going to make a speech.
I'm just going to say thank you, you're wonderful people.
Many, many thanks for all your help and support.
God bless.
The last surgery, people didn't have a complaint.
They just wanted to see him and meet him.
People were making things up, I think, problems they had.
So, after that, we had to...
And of course security, they said we had to change it, so now we still have a surgery but it's either held here or it's held in the Labour Club, which is easy for them to police.
The area's patrolled and covered 24 hours a day, which some think is wonderful to have policemen around 24 hours a day but it can be intrusive.
They are patrolling throughout those 24 hours.
It's the best thing in the world.
We never lock the door, leave the keys in the car.
We just go on holiday and never have to worry about anything.
It's been marvellous, the security.
There's been no bother whatsoever.
Sedgefield had got used to being the centre of attention.
But May 1st, 1997, was something else.
Anthony Charles Lynton Blair, the Labour Party candidate.
I remember being in the Trimdon Labour Club that night.
The floor was so sticky that your feet were stuck to it, yet everybody, on the ceiling somehow, as in walked this bloke that people had known for 15 years who had overnight become the Prime Minister.
I don't think anyone was really ready for that huge step change.
At that point, I realised this man was going to be the Prime Minister and our relationship would never be the same again because it has to change.
It was fantastic.
Like a dream, really.
We all flew down to London together.
It was surreal, really.
It was fantastic.
We went straight to the Festival Hall and the atmosphere was just unbelievable.
A new dawn has broken, has it not?
Just as he said, "A new day is dawning," the sun came out.
Brilliant sunshine.
And I thought, "Good God, when he's finished this speech, "he'll walk over to number ten across...
He'll not take the bridge, "he'll just walk straight across the water."
I had my camera, you know, just competing with the world's media for the best shots.
Cherie just caught a glance of me and waved just before Tony made his speech on the steps of Downing Street.
He'd been woken up at about 3.30 am to be told about Diana so he made a speech on the green, just outside of church.
I just remember a really sombre, almost sullen-faced Blair.
She was the People's Princess.
And that's how she will stay, how she will remain.
It was such a contrast from the scene, I guess, four months earlier which was where the Labour Club was and where this immense jubilation had taken place with people absolutely on the ceiling.
So, by chance, Sedgefield was again centre stage in world events.
But momentous times aside, there was still time for everyday life.
We were just refurbishing the kitchen and Tony came in and had a coffee and a sandwich.
And of course he was joking about the wall.
He just signed it "Lovely decor".
He put the date on and signed it "Tony Blair."
We've actually been invited several times up to Mirabella to do some catering at the house, which has been a real experience.
We got a call about five o'clock in the afternoon.
Downing Street.
"Can you do dinner for ten?"
I said, "Yeah, course I can.
When?"
"Oh, tonight."
Of course, I know the PM likes his fresh fish, so I rang up our fish man.
He said, "He's coming, is he?"
I said, "Aye."
I said, "I need scallops, I need cod, I need this, I need that, "sea bass and so on."
He came up in his car and brought everything for us.
John Burton's daughter got married in the village and we were bridesmaids, as well as Tony's daughter.
So Tony was obviously there.
There was a big wedding reception as well and outside the church there was a lot of press taking photos.
At the wedding reception they got to be themselves and chat to all the people they knew.
Leo's christening was at Sedgefield and I feel quite privileged to have been able to attend that.
I didn't want to say, "When's the baptism?"
Because I couldn't presume I would be doing the baptism.
I thought maybe the Cardinal or someone in London would be deputed to do that.
Cherie's mother said, "We'll be coming up to Sedgefield for the baptism."
That was the end of it.
In due course, they came and I baptised Leo and then he went his way.
I looked round there.
I was amazed to see that apart from the immediate family, a large number of people there were people I recognised from television.
It did seem to me to be already a very dangerous thing that somebody should seem to have so few, as it were, ordinary friends.
Immediately I felt kind of protective towards him in a way and my job would be to pray for him and help to keep his feet on the ground.
On his visits, Tony Blair had a chance to hear how his policies were going down and to find out what needed fixing.
Doorframes that were coming away from walls, concrete slabs that were slipping and constitute danger.
The cost of removing asbestos.
I think he was surprised.
I think when he saw the real detail of it, and I did take him to some of the worst areas, I think he was surprised.
He wanted to know more.
It's not an opportunity everyone gets and it was by accident because it happens to be our constituency, but it's something you should take with both hands and go for it and tell him like it is.
And I certainly didn't dress up any issues.
Some visits were more uncomfortable than others.
Obviously this is a very difficult situation indeed.
It's not one any of us wanted to be in.
Fujitsu panicked, pulled the plug on our plant.
It's a result of what's happened around the world in the semi-conductor market.
When they announced it was closing, he sort of came out as a PR exercise with it being his constituency.
Appease the workforce but I think our politest people were probably nicer to him than they felt like at the time.
..Be affected by the closure. That's the most important thing we can do.
As the realities of Government kicked in, those who'd become friends in Sedgefield knew what their role was.
If he's got something on his mind that he's worried about, tell us.
I think the kind of relationship we have with him, he knows that he can trust us implicitly, because we've been with him so long from the beginning and the loyalty's unconditional, really.
He needs to know that there are people like that who aren't going to run to the press.
Somebody rang me up from London and said, "What are you paying?"
We had this full-page article.
Big picture of Downing Street and the PM and a big picture of ministers and me.
Full-page article as if I'd given an interview and I hadn't.
I had to ring the agents and say it wasn't us.
At first I used to get very down about it.
I thought, "It's horrible, they don't really know him."
It isn't very nice, I don't like it.
I don't like it when they have a go at either him or Cherie.
They are a lovely family.
Who would want to hurt them?
But some local people who met Blair less frequently were beginning to doubt his ability to deliver on their doorsteps.
Three years on, Woodham Community Technology College played host to the Prime Minister again.
He did look, I have to say, a little bit older than the intervening three years.
There were one or two signs of stress, but I think he welcomed the opportunity to relax.
For me personally, I was beginning to wonder whether there was that raw idealism and that clear vision still in place.
I'm talking about the Government generally, not necessarily Tony Blair, although he's obviously the Leader of the Government.
I began to wonder if it was frayed at the edges.
And, just as in the rest of Britain, in Sedgefield, pleas from friends profoundly opposed to the war in Iraq brought real division.
He hadn't taken any notice of the Pope and the Archbishop of Canterbury so why take any notice of me?
While I'm not in any position to make any judgement about him, really, in the eyes of God, it distresses me that the two most notable warmongers of recent times, in this part of the world anyway, are two people who claim to be church people, and that saddens me very much because it's normally very much the last resort and we weren't at the last resort when we went to war.
I will never forget when the Black Stallion helicopters flew over the trees, just the immense size of these things coming down and there were police ringing the field.
They just landed in the centre of this very, very grotty playing field and to see these colliery terraces that fringe the field and just the immense interest by the American media of all of them scrabbling around the Trimdons, not knowing where the hell they were was just extraordinary.
When they landed, George, or Mr Bush, saw that we have a cow in the garden and the first thing he noticed from the helicopter before it landed was this cow, which my wife had situated right in the middle of the lawn.
I would never, ever have thought that we'd have that sort of person, or that sort of, well, response in Trimdon here.
It was such a big operation, as you can imagine, and it was liaising with the Secret Service teams, and I co-ordinated what they called the motorcade, and the transportation of the President.
The police were trying to keep us off the road, so everybody crammed into the back yard, and after about half an hour, they come out here, straight past here, and we saw George Bush, on our side of the car.
I've got him on my video, as well, and off they went to Sedgefield, for fish and chips.
The whole village was closed, basically.
You couldn't get in, couldn't get out, and the police presence was utterly unbelievable.
We weren't open.
I strolled down the street to have a look, and it was just absolutely crazy, and people were told, "If you poke your head out of the window, "these guys are going to ask questions later."
When President Bush visited Sedgefield, we felt it was very important to make as much of a protest as we could, as we were allowed to make, because it did seem as though so much damage had been done that to try to pass this off as, in some way, a welcome individual human being was just something that we couldn't accept.
George Bush!
Terrorist!
Tony Blair!
The whole air was just full of noise, and there were sharp-shooters on every particular gantry possible, and then inside the pub, everything was just...
A completely different world, everyone was smiling and happy, and there was all this hatred, and placards, and "Blood on your hands" signs outside, smiling George shaking hands with the landlord, and sitting down as if it was a completely different world.
I thought George Bush was a very, very nice chap, considering he's one of the biggest men in the world.
He was a bit magnificent, even.
I had a word or two.
I had my photograph taken with him at the Dun Cow.
He had just met our daughter, cos she re-introduced us, and he mentioned the cow in the garden.
I have a very dear priest friend, who was actually in Las Vegas at the time, and he telephoned me on the night.
"By the way, Jack," he said, "this is the end of a beautiful friendship", because he was very anti-Bush, and he'd seen the picture, that was flashed around the world, of course, and he'd seen me on the television with George Bush, having the lunch in the Dun Cow.
Well, I sat next to President Bush, and I remember them saying, you know, "You must say Mr President and Mrs Bush", so I'm trying to get my tongue around saying "Mr President" all the time, and that was funny, but he was a very nice man.
I just asked him questions about how his father was, and how his girls were coping with him being President, and all of that.
"I regret to inform you, Mr Keys, that Thomas was killed this morning, in Iraq, in the line of duty."
I will never forget those words.
They haunt me to this day, and I just felt he died deceived by his Prime Minister.
There was a memorial service for the fallen in Iraq.
Tony Blair was there, mingling with the bereaved families, and all I said to him was, "My son died for his country.
"You sent my son to war for WMD.
He was deceived.
"You're a father, I'm a father", and he said, "I regret Tom's death, but it was the right thing to do, to remove Saddam."
And I said, "Are you sorry that he's died?"
He said, "I regret his death, but it was the right thing to do."
He would not say he was sorry for my son's death, and I thought, "Right, I'll push this as far as I can.
"I'll be an eternal thorn in your side for this.
There are 85 soldiers killed, there are 850 wounded...
So the thorn came to lobby Sedgefield's voters, and urge them to stop Tony Blair's bid to win a third term as Prime Minister.
We had him up for election here.
We were just hit, bang, bang by the world's media, hoping that, of course, he was gonna lose his seat on the Iraq issue.
I thought, "How on earth am I gonna make inroads into this area, "where Labour is literally a religion?"
You could have an MP that you could meet.
Have you ever met your MP?
I haven't.
I think he craves the kudos, the esteem of having your local MP as a Prime Minister, but when you ask, "Have you ever spoken to him?
"Have you had a surgery with him?
Nobody's met him.
They only ever meet his agent, John Burton, but it's just the esteem, I believe, of having the Prime Minister as your MP.
"Oh, you haven't come to take on our Tony, have you?"
"Our Tony", as if he's a bosom buddy!
I think he's convinced that they did the right thing, and I think some of the reaction to it has hurt him a little bit.
He wouldn't be normal if it didn't.
People were still at the polls at the time, and it seemed to have escaped his mind, and suddenly, there, in the middle of this service, we were aware at the back was Tony Blair and John Burton, and they worshipped, and they took communion, and we celebrated the peace with them, but sadly, they disappeared again just before the end of the service, so we didn't have a chance to talk to them.
The mood in the Labour Club was completely different to what it had been on election night in '97.
There was far more anxiety as the results had come in, and everyone was really, really downcast.
It was a bit like a pop star, really, on an end of world tour, his latest album having kind of bombed, really.
There was a real feeling that we were reaching the end of the road, and people were already asking, "How long are you going to go on?"
I wanted to catch his eye, it was firmly cast in another direction.
It was like a glaze.
He wouldn't look towards me at all.
I didn't even follow my notes, and I just said it from my heart.
Maybe it was better to do it that way, but had I realised that the world's cameras were on me, there's a few more things I would have liked to have said.
I hope in my heart that one day, the Prime Minister may be able to say sorry.
That one day, he will say sorry to the families of the bereaved, and one day, the Prime Minister might be able to visit wounded soldiers in hospital.
Then our campaign will not have been in vain.
'I was wearing my son's suit.
'All the campaign, I wore my son's suit,' which I'm wearing now, in honour of Thomas, and I always do, whenever I feel I'm representing him.
I'm proud of him.
He died a brave young man, along with his colleagues, and he died serving his country.
Our job is to serve people.
It's what I've tried to do in Sedgefield.
It's what we'll try to do for the country.
The voters of Sedgefield returned their MP with an increased majority.
It doesn't matter what your politics are.
At the end of the day, he's a serving Prime Minister, and the fact that he comes into our house, and chooses to dine here, I think it's quite an achievement.
Even if I move away from the village, and live somewhere else, when I'm older, and I've got children, they'll go to their history class, and learn about Tony Blair and when he was Prime Minister, they'll be able to come home, and I'll say, "Well, I can help you out with that."
I've never had a personal feeling of animosity against him.
He's never done me, personally, any more harm than he's done everybody else, and, I think, a lot less than he's done himself.
I want Tony to be happy for the rest of his life, doing something he wants to do, and for us, it'll be time for us to retire.
Our lives have been enriched.
Tony might go, but we can live for 20 years, at least, on the tales that we can tell amongst ourselves.
I think that he will sell his house in Sedgefield, and it's unlikely that they'll ever see him again.
I'll sit and read me book, and play me guitar, and phone him up now and again, and see how he's getting on.